In the remaining jungle of Borneo,
lives a tribe of nomadic hunter-gatherers.
They're known for their survival skills
and for the deadly poison they use
on their blowpipe darts
the Penan
My name is Raphael Treza.
I'm a musician and film-maker
I’m going to spend the next three months
with the Penan tribe of Malaysia
My journey begins in Kuala Lumpur
Then a flight to Borneo
the third largest island in the world
bigger than France or Texas
it's divided into 3 territories
Indonesian Kalimantan in the south
which means burning weather island
and Brunei and Malaysian Borneo in the north
From the air
I catch a glimpse of what the palm oil industry
has done to this country
I land in Sarawak
a Malaysian state that’s seen massive deforestation.
A land where activists get killed
or disappear
During a period of over fifty years
the Malaysian government has overseen the destruction
of the vast majority of Borneo’s primary rainforest
selling it for billions of dollars as timber
Half of all the world’s annual supply of tropical timber
comes from Borneo
and it’s replaced with rubber plantations
and oil palm trees
the products of which are now used
in around half of all packaged supermarket goods.
Very few national parks have been created in Sarawak
to protect what is considered to be
the oldest and most diverse ecosystems on Earth
hosting one third of all plant species on the planet
and an estimated 3 million insect species
Less than 10% of Sarawak’s primary rainforest
remains intact
and where the land still looks green
it's mostly secondary forest growing for more timber
The forest grows back so densely
that it’s no longer habitable for its biggest
and most endangered species
like the orangutan and sun bears
The Penan were the only tribe of hunters-gatherers
able to live as nomads
in the primary rainforest of Borneo
settling for a couple of months in temporary huts,
collecting only what they needed
before moving on to other hunting grounds
A peaceful, good-natured people
the 15,000 Penan who lived here
didn’t stand a chance
against the powerful logging companies
supported by a mafia state government
When they started blocking logging roads,
many were arrested and even tortured.
Most of them ended up in cities,
forgetting their precious survival knowledge.
Today, only a few families
have kept their traditional way of life.
But as crucial space is missing,
they are forced to live part-time in camps and villages.
Bala is a semi-nomadic Penan tribesman.
He’s recently had to take shelter in a village
when his forest was cut down.
He's using a bamboo segment as a container,
to fill with the deadly Tajem,
the poison applied to the tips of his hunting darts.
The Tajem tree,
or Antiaris Toxicaria,
grows up to forty meters high.
It’s widespread all-over south Asia and tropical Africa.
In its raw form, the sap is deadly
when it enters the bloodstream,
causing lethal cardiac arrhythmia
but, through a special refining process,
the penan make it even more powerful.
It is then fatal, in less than two minutes,
depending on the size of the prey.
It’s ideal for hunting
as it doesn't contaminate the meat
The Penan rely on foreign trade to procure iron
in return for resin, animal skins and handicrafts.
Bala carefully cleans
the residual deadly sap from his machete
Bala pours the harvested latex
into a pot made of dried leaves.
These pots are also made from green leaves
for boiling water and cooking meat.
He is careful to heat it
at just the right distance from the flame
to avoid boiling the sap.
As night falls
on the forest of Borneo
many species risk leaving the safety of their burrows.
To make the poison more powerful,
the Penan follow a special recipe.
They combine several plants in specific proportions.
The darts are then coated in the poisonous mixture,
dried by the fire,
and are ready to use.
Richard is a sedentary Penan.
He was born ten years after his family
was forced out of the jungle in the nineties.
He works in a nearby national park.
He's from one of the few villages that still has access
to the untouched rainforest
and reserve the right
to practice traditional blowpipe hunting.
He's joined by his cousin.
They search for their favorite meat,
the wild boar.
It’s become harder to find
due to human activities
around the border of the park.
Blowpipe hunting
is a matter of stealth and patience.
During the day
every animal is on their guard.
This squirrel got lucky.
Richie has found some bamboo shoots.
They will provide a vegetarian meal for tonight.
Later, they’re boiled
to clear the cyanide it naturally contains.
The rivers running through the national parks
are clear and free of pollution from logging,
which erodes the ground
and makes the water muddy.
The Penan can still practice fishing here.
They use homemade spear-guns.
They also fish in swamps, using bread.
It takes only three seconds to catch a fish.
Now it’s my turn to try.
A few Penan families still live as semi-nomads
in the remote jungle.
Langub, a sedentary Penan
guides me to meet them.
He needs the help of a Penan couple
who live on the way.
We arrive at a camp
built with the help of some sedentary Penan
to facilitate meetings
between the nomads and their relatives
who have left the forest.
Saya lives here a couple of months a year.
With his two sons,
Tyon and Ajai,
his wife
and his two daughters.
The Penan keep female names secret to outsiders,
so, they’ll remain a mystery.
For lunch,
there’s rice,
turtle
and a mix of tapioca flour the Penan call Naon,
which tastes like water.
Their main source of food
would traditionally come from the sago palm tree.
Saya and his kids are taking me to harvest its trunk.
The Penan take great care to not damage its roots,
so the palm will continue to thrive.
He first collects some moss called Jakah,
an essential survival element
used to light fires.
The palm heart is typically made into a nutritious,
non-perishable flour,
but it's also eaten raw.
At the junction of two paths,
Saya shows me Oroo,
the Penan’s way of communicating
with other members of the tribe,
using signs made of branches.
The code always begins with the Penan motto,
Jah Kenin
“We have the same heart”
In the few villages bordering reserved areas,
the Penan have been offered jobs
in the national parks
and are allowed to hunt
in untouched regions of rainforest.
In tourist places like these,
the government appears to have made an effort
to build a brand-new hospital,
but as I'll learn later,
nothing has been arranged for the Penan
who’ve been forced to settle down
in remote villages.
Like most tribes in Borneo,
Penan families share living accommodation,
called longhouses.
Their woven craft is made of rattan,
a vine that can reach a length of more than 200 meters
and can be crushed to use as a natural toothbrush.
It’s now being replaced by plastic.
The Penan used to be animist,
worshipping the forest spirit
called Ballei
Like most tribes in Borneo,
they’ve been Christianized.
Nyapun was one of the first Penan chiefs
to be forced to settle down.
He says he's probably 89 years old.
The Penan used to live in the present.
The canopy would hide the sky
so they couldn’t count moon phases or years.
He is gathering fern shoots
and tapioca leaves for lunch.
Like most tribesmen in rural Borneo,
Nyapun never leaves his house without a weapon
for self-defense.
The spear attached to the end of his blowpipe
is a reliable secondary weapon
Tribal wars are still in living memory
and encountering wild animals
like giant pythons and sun bears
could still be a deadly.
Nyapun's second wife
plays nose flute.
They live in this compound
with their children and grandchildren.
Two villagers guide me to a remote Penan camp
at the end of a logging road.
These dangerous, abandoned roads
are prone to landslides and sinkholes.
A few pockets of primary forest
were spared from the chainsaws.
Penan are known to be very shy,
which makes their adaptation to the outside
very challenging.
The villagers have a hornbill as a pet.
Hornbills are the emblem of Sarawak.
Many different species exist all over Asia.
Like the Great Hornbill,
here filmed in Cambodia.
Older Penan folk suffer most
from their lost nomadic lifestyle,
and struggle to adapt to life in the villages.
Many suffer from depression
or have lost their minds.
I'm back with Bala.
He shows me how to make Penan barkcloth.
He cuts a Beripun tree
and beats it
to remove the bark from the trunk.
The Penan use over 1,500 names for plants.
Most of them are used in their ethnobotany.
He softens the bark
by beating it.
These were the traditional loin-cloths
until cotton replaced them.
This plant is used by the Penan to treat snake bites.
It's one of the most useful medicinal plants
in the jungle of Borneo,
which is loaded with deadly snakes.
This same plant
saved the life of Swiss ethnologist and activist
Bruno Manser.
He spent six years living with the Penan
in the eighties,
unifying and rallying them against the loggers
by helping to block logging roads.
The Malaysian government put a price on his head.
He disappeared in the jungle of Sarawak in 2000,
following his return from Europe.
He was declared dead in 2005
and remains as a hero for the Penan.
Though I hope I won't need it,
I decide to keep some for the rest of my trip.
Another very powerful medicinal plant in Borneo
is Kratom.
It's known to treat opiate and alcohol addiction.
It's also used against fever
and to relieve stress and anxiety.
I now travel to the south of Sarawak,
near the Indonesian border,
to meet the Iban,
who are known as the head hunters.
Their name is also the Lakya
which means “the strong men”.
They used to practice head hunting on other tribes,
including the Penan,
and some families still keep skulls
as trophies in their longhouses.
The Iban don't use blowpipes for hunting,
opting for regular guns.
Even though head hunting officially ceased a century ago,
the Iban are still remembered as merciless warriors,
and guides still advise against entering
Iban longhouses without invitation.
They are famous for their tattoos.
Tattoos represent an important life event
like becoming a father.
For the first head taken,
a tattoo was made on the hand
the Entegulun
The Iban now mix their traditional tattoos
with Western styles
and foreign travelers come to get Iban tattoos.
At Saya's camp,
the family is preparing for a trip
through the jungle.
Saya's daughter is petting the family's monkey.
The Penan use them as guards,
giving a signal when danger is near.
The family prepares to build a camp
en route to their next living place.
They choose an uphill spot
away from mosquitoes and falling trees.
Under such changeable weather conditions,
they must be able to build a rainproof shelter
in under an hour.
As part of Penan fashion,
they sometimes like to dye their hands
with red leaves.
The family occasionally leave the forest
to trade meat in the villages,
but they're often isolated for months
and must light their fires without using a lighter.
With his knife,
Saya strikes a firestone that he found in the river.
Sparks fall on the moss,
igniting it.
More moss and a bit of cloth
help the flames grow.
To illuminate the hut at night,
the Penan use a plant candle,
made from the pod of a vine.
It provides light for up to an hour.
It rains almost every day in the jungle.
Punyau, a readily-combustible wood,
is cut and briefly dried above the fire.
Tyon is making Penan forks,
or Atip,
some versatile and effective cutlery,
which are easy and fast to craft.
I leave the nomads
to meet a displaced community
at the center of Sarawak.
There is no public transport,
so, I decide to hitchhike.
The village is hours away from any other camp
and I’m travelling next to 1000 liters of diesel.
I come with a present,
the book written by Bruno Manser.
They can't read it,
but it contains many drawings
of what are now rare animals and plants.
Some villagers are preparing their blowpipes
for hunting the next day.
Penan blowpipes are crafted from ironwood,
the hardest wood in the jungle.
Their making is a long process,
drilling by hand on a platform.
The use of wooden blowpipes
only appeared in the middle of the 20th century
when the Penan acquired iron drills.
They were previously made of bamboo.
Once shaped as a tube
and sanded down with a special leaf,
the blowpipe is precise up to forty meters.
Tribesmen in Borneo
have developed a very distinctive style
combining modern outfits
with traditional survival gear and jewelry
High socks help protect against leeches.
They wear rattan bracelets
and wild boar tusks.
Apart from an unused room
presented as a school
the government has done nothing for these families,
in the hopes that they will eventually
migrate to the cities.
The head of the camp wants to talk to me
about the situation here.
Sarawak is home
to what was once thought to be the largest
cave on earth,
until one bigger was recently discovered in Vietnam.
Three and a half million bats
make their home inside.
Every evening,
they leave the cave in search of fruit and insects.
They form swarms
to confuse predators like eagles.
After nightfall in the camp,
the families gather
to watch the only Kung Fu movie they have.
This giant cicada
is one of a thousand different cicada species
in Borneo
In the morning,
the village kids get ready for hunting.
Lia, Asik,
and their little brothers Yung and Jokim
find a thorny palm
whose soft heart is used for the darts’ fletching.
Without this crucial element,
their entire survival in the jungle
would be jeopardized.
The plug is carved to the right width
using a wooden guide.
The season for wild fruit
lasts only three months a year,
and boars have become rare in this secondary forest.
As a result, the Penan are forced
to rely on supplementary foods,
like birds and pygmy squirrels.
Using the poison, small prey dies instantly.
Yung has found a plant
used by kids as hair gel.
Stingless bees come to drink on our skin.
Giant wild bees also make swarms
on the remaining tall trees.
The Penan use a distinctive tongue clicking
to express surprise and approval
It’s time for me
to leave the Penan.
A people for whom kindness,
generosity and courage
is a way of life.
Their ingenuity,
and the elegant solutions they employ
to thrive in some of the most challenging
and complex environments
must not be lost.
All of humanity
could benefit from Penan knowledge of plants
and their understanding of nature.
One day
the tables will turn,
and the wealth of every country
will be defined
by the nature they hold
when that day comes,
the last Penan families living in the wild
may have left the rainforest
along
with all their secrets.